<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-01T17:43:40+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jamie on Software</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">The trade-offs are worth it</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/01/01/the-tradeoffs-are-worth-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The trade-offs are worth it" /><published>2022-01-01T16:34:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T16:34:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/01/01/the-tradeoffs-are-worth-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/01/01/the-tradeoffs-are-worth-it.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m very prone to greener-grass thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s important to acknowledge that the grass is greener, because, well it is. Sometimes you’re not in the best possible timeline, and bringing it to your own attention is the first step toward changing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s often unhelpful, too, and can trap you into a cycle of distraction and dissatisfaction. You change something, because the grass over there is greener, and you reinforce the preferences you have for novelty. The less you develop the ability to stick with something, focus, persevere, the more difficult it becomes the next time you must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more vulnerable you become to your own whims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more often you throw away something valuable, because you’re suffering under some sort of novelty bias and what appears to be objectively better is simply fresher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it can be useful to reframe how you view your current situation. When I regret some decision because the alternative looks easier, or if I suspect I have made a mistake, I can find solace in the knowledge that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It can be easy to forget you’re making trade-offs explicitly and knowingly;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, the &lt;strong&gt;tradeoffs are generally worth it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beginning of anything requires a first step. A new job, a new purchase, a new skill or hobby, a new relationship. If you’re a thoughtful and goal-oriented person, you will consider whether this the right step for you. Something that might appear to be obvious at the time might be a mistake later, and you know this, so you take your time, weigh up your options. Consider the pros and cons and decide to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, you’re in the honeymoon phase. The cons are irrelevant. The pros are even better than you expected. You enjoy the present. You look forward to the future with anticipation, with giddiness, with glee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some days later, the pros and cons look evenly balanced. You’re less interested than you once were, but stasis is a powerful force, so you do nothing about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some days further, the cons are now what is salient. What began as small pet peeves or niggling doubts have blossomed. The cons are so overwhelming, so frustrating, that you cannot imagine why you could ever have thought the pros might outweigh them (or, hell, even counterbalance them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What seemed like a good idea now looks like a set of inappropriate, naïve preferences borne from the brain of somebody &lt;strong&gt;who knew less than what you do now&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing. You made those tradeoffs. You considered the pros, you considered the cons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have missed some of the cons initially; not everybody gets it right first time. But this also applies to the pros. Are there not things about your role, your club, your partner, your commitment, whatever it is, that are unexpectedly pleasant, as well as unexpectedly not-so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it appears not, then consider this: even if you were able to predict everything a priori, do you think you’d be weighing the cons and pros appropriately after the cons have become so aggravating that you felt the need to reweigh them in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People only really reflect on whether their decisions were correct when they have reason to suspect that they weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People don’t look to upend the boat when they’re enjoying the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your re-evaluation may be happening from a place of more intimate knowledge, but it’s also happening from a place of discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely times when you should re-evaluate. When you are being harmed. When you have good reason to suspect you misjudged it all initially. Or when your preferences have changed significantly since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are lots of times when you shouldn’t. When, were you to reflect in a pro-dominant phase, you’d conclude quite differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grass is always greener, Jamie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tradeoffs are usually worth it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">I’m very prone to greener-grass thinking.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Books I Wish Existed</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2021/05/16/books-i-wish-existed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Books I Wish Existed" /><published>2021-05-16T16:16:37+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-16T16:16:37+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2021/05/16/books-i-wish-existed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2021/05/16/books-i-wish-existed.html">&lt;p&gt;For a while I’ve been collecting a list of interesting book-length projects. Since I’m never going to write the bloody things, I figured it’d be better to throw them into the light of day and see what daylight makes of them.
Here is a preliminary, first stab at a list of books I wish existed: books that haven’t been written yet, but could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A collection of short books on the history and interpretation of U.S. constitutional amendments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One under-explored feature of the US constitution is its deep cultural, as well as judicial, role in modern American politics. Each amendment has its own motivations, historical context, and judicial precedent; but each amendment also serves as the starting point for contemporary arguments for or against certain policies: even, today, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/im-a-first-amendment-scholar-and-i-think-big-tech-should-be-left-alone-153287&quot;&gt;the policies of private companies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to see a series of short, concise, focussed books – think roughly the length and depth of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.veryshortintroductions.com/&quot;&gt;OUP Very Short Introductions&lt;/a&gt; series – with each volume focussed around an amendment to the U.S. constitution. Each book could discuss the amendment’s historical context, important cases in its subsequent judicial precedent, and the moral and legal and institutional justifications for the amendment and how they have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most amendments would have their own volume, while some of the more arcane amendments might be bundled together, where appropriate. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty-first_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution&quot;&gt;18th &amp;amp; 21st&lt;/a&gt; are a natural pairing; the 13th, 14th and 15th sit snugly together in terms of their shared historical context, but are perhaps each significant enough, with their own rich set of continuing precedent and relevance, for their own volumes; perhaps the 3rd, 4th and 5th. It might also be interesting to conclude the series with a volume on the amendments that didn’t get passed: amongst &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_proposed_amendments_to_the_United_States_Constitution&quot;&gt;many others&lt;/a&gt;, the ERA, balanced budget amendments, the We the People amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeing Like A Startup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott’s &lt;em&gt;Seeing Like A State&lt;/em&gt; is an excellent piece of political epistemology, not because he makes a powerful moral argument to curtail the absolute power of the state – which he does – nor because of the trenchant analysis he applies to the material and sociopolitical conditions under which the tools of statecraft are likely to be abused – which he gives – but because it grounds the analysis in a &lt;em&gt;Weltanschauung&lt;/em&gt;, an all-encompassing frame of reference, a set of spectacles that underpin the identity of those who wear them. To see like a state is not just to see the world a certain way, to plan with a specific framework, to write with a specific dictionary, but also to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; somebody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t the same true of startup-land? Isn’t working in a startup with its techno-optimism and its studied disregard of conventional wisdom and Disruption with a Capital D a form of world-view? Weren’t we decades ahead on remote work and Agile / Lean Startup approaches to product development? Don’t startups, especially tech startups, have a distinctive set of incentives and respond to a distinctive set of internal and external cues? Isn’t this weird (physical or virtual) Bay Area we inhabit a conduit for a specific mode of thought, a Weltanschauung, a pair of spectacles?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A full-length biography of Évariste Galois&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Évariste Galois died aged 20, after being shot in the stomach with a pistol. He died a gregarious yet unlikable, angry young man, but he bequeathed us a small elliptic body of mathematical work that has &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galois_theory&quot;&gt;proven&lt;/a&gt; to be incredibly fertile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short biographies that accompany discussions of his work are useful and evocative, but focus almost exclusively on either his precociousness, or the Potemkin-romanticism of his death. His life was short but full of activity, sadness, anger, intense adolescence, mental illness and revolutionary politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Evariste-Galois-fabrication-ic%C3%B4ne-math%C3%A9matique/dp/2713223172&quot;&gt;best biography of him so far (fr)&lt;/a&gt; focusses on Galois-as-mathematical-figure (‘personne’ vs ‘personnage’). I’d like to see a full-length biography of Galois-as-boy and Galois-as-man, as well as Galois-as-mathematician: something that draws out the dynamics of a Republican and Bonapartite household in restoration Paris, the stability of his mother and bipolarity of his father (who himself committed suicide when Évariste was 15), the friends and foes, real and imagined, that shaped this troubled young boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to write this book for a while, but have &lt;a href=&quot;http://jamierumbelow.net/paused.html&quot;&gt;put the project on hold&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps I’ll resurrect it one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uses and abuses of popular science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effective communication of science is incredibly important. What the electorate understands and values about scientific output can translate meaningfully into policy outcomes, on the one hand, and our continued ability to discover more about the world on the other. (At its limit, it can cause &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rogers_Commission_Report&quot;&gt;deadly incentives failures&lt;/a&gt; when the scientific bureaucracy needs to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teacher_in_Space_Project&quot;&gt;reengage a science-saturated public&lt;/a&gt;).  Simplifying without talking down is a tough job, and the&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Sagan&quot;&gt; very&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B00AQLFQKW/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;best&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://timharford.com/&quot;&gt; writers&lt;/a&gt; do it with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Jay_Gould&quot;&gt;elegance&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Hofstadter&quot;&gt;wit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_Sacks&quot;&gt;humanity&lt;/a&gt;. But so much of it is reductionist, factually incorrect, statistically ignorant, sensationalist drivel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing about science poorly harms us all. Being excessively confident about scientists’ predictions – “toast causes cancer!” – shifts our focus onto the wrong things, or erodes trust in the output of science when it turns out that, you know, the world might be a little more complicated. Being excessively cynical about science’s output is so often a tiresome postmodern ploy to import political solutions to yet-understood social issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to see a book on popular science and the popularisation of science: what good it can do when it’s good, what harm it can do when it’s bad, and how we can get more of the former and less of the latter. I’d also like to learn more about how science fiction fits into all this. We will never get to a stage where science is not weaponised in one direction or another – discovery is, as the physicists of the Manhattan Project discovered, the beginning of the moral story, not the end of it – but with a better understanding of how science is reported, we might be able to give people the tools to at least discount the views of the most egregious of offenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; science look like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way that modern science is structured – the categories and classifications of physics, biology, chemistry, computer science, mathematics, philosophy, the social sciences – forms a reasonably arbitrary and path-dependent structure. A few changes in how humans organised themselves at various stages, how projects got funded, and which questions happened to be salient (for cultural or contingent material reasons), and we have a very different body of knowledge, structured along different lines, today. What, for instance, would modern AI look like if the centre of gravity in computer science hadn’t drifted away from cybernetics and the HCI-focussed research tradition during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Dream-Machine-M-Mitchell-Waldrop/dp/1732265119&quot;&gt;ARPA golden years&lt;/a&gt;, and toward applied mathematics and algorithm design? What could biology look like if our best mathematicians were more interested in biological systems rather than physical systems? What would Newton have done if he hadn’t spent so much time pursuing alchemy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A good moral, economic and psychological investigation into paternalism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a set of libertarian-ish (which is to say, mostly negative) aesthetic reactions to paternalism, and, in a trivial sense, ‘paternalism is bad’ seems true by definition – at least on a normative reading of ‘paternalism’. Naturally, these intuitions have come into much sharper focus throughout the pandemic. But state interventions in private lives are nothing new, in many cases they are basically uncontroversial (e.g. seat belts) and there are a whole host of &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/paternalism/&quot;&gt;moral&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/000282803321947001&quot;&gt;economic&lt;/a&gt; arguments in favour as well as against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps paternalistic reasoning is our default mode of thought and respect for individual freedom only gets bolted on in certain contexts? If you really believe that such-and-such a lifestyle is immoral, harmful materially and spiritually to he who practices it, why wouldn’t you want to intervene? Liberalism is a position most have to contort themselves into.
I’d like to see a modern book-length treatment of this subject, exploring the changing relationship between individual and society, ideally within a framework that make sense of big data, the long death of privacy, and crypto- or techno-libertarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aesthetics in politics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hume never got to finish his &lt;a href=&quot;https://davidhume.org/texts/t/ad1739&quot;&gt;‘examination of morals, politics, and criticism’&lt;/a&gt;, but if he had, I imagine much of the project would be spent grounding political discourse in terms of human sentiments like approval and disgust. Jonathan Haidt offers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Righteous-Mind-Divided-Politics-Religion/dp/0141039167&quot;&gt;a modern-day version of this story&lt;/a&gt;, arguing for the centrality of psychological states in understanding politics and religious discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one thing that often gets ignored, I think, is how much &lt;em&gt;aesthetics&lt;/em&gt; play a part. People find views they dislike not just disagreeable but &lt;em&gt;ugly&lt;/em&gt;, and often detached logical reasoning takes a backseat to matters of taste. I’d wager that a lot of opposition to virtue signalling, for instance, is simply that it seems distasteful, or uncouth, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To what extent do we elevate matters of taste to matters of shared social importance? (There’s an interesting Twitter thread &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vgr/status/1350300376205938688?s=24&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on conservatism and aesthetic sense, which might begin to address these issues.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The House of Uncommons: the rise and fall of excellence in politics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why has politics lost its cultural cachet? Why do we pay our governors so little relative to other, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dollarsandsense.sg/heres-much-singapores-president-cabinet-ministers-paid-salary/&quot;&gt;arguably better run&lt;/a&gt;, countries – and certainly less than a lot of private-sector high-status jobs? Are our politicians getting more incompetent and panderous, as they do indeed seem to be? When was the golden era of the politician? What characteristics should we try to select for? Given the unpredictability of democracy and the epistemic credentials of the average voter, how can we reshape our institutions to better encourage the selection of these characteristics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Aesthetics of Programming Languages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that often gets lost amongst the computer science jargon and expediencies of writing functional software is that there’s an important &lt;em&gt;aesthetic&lt;/em&gt; dimension to programming, a concern with the beauty of the code and algorithms we write. We throw around words like ‘beautiful’ when we talk about code, but we’re usually just gesturing toward some muddy intuitive notion, something like ‘clean’. There’s been little attempt to define these words more rigorously, or explore other aesthetic or aesthetic-adjacent virtues, such as simplicity, or parsimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not merely syntactic, either. Much of what a programmer does is invent abstractions, extract out pieces of a system into reusable and more generic chunks. Some abstractions are intuitively better than others. But on what grounds? It’s not just “how widely applicable is this thing”, or “how performant is this thing”, or “how few lines of code does this thing take to implement or call”. There’s a notion of &lt;em&gt;expressivity&lt;/em&gt;, the capacity for the abstraction to open and close the right set of logical doors, that is crucially important, and, crucially, misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It runs deeper than just the code that actually gets written. Different language design decisions force us to &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about our code in different ways, and to structure our programmes along different fault lines. Type systems force us to think about our domain before we think about the processes we apply in that domain. Pure functional languages force us to think about the flow and transformation of data. Different languages, sometimes, though by no means always, designed for different tasks, start with different mental primitives which change both how we write code now, and how the norms of the broader language ecosystem evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great irony of programming: instructing computers can be a deeply human thing. It would be fun to see a thoughtful little book exploring these questions in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="politics" /><category term="startups" /><summary type="html">For a while I’ve been collecting a list of interesting book-length projects. Since I’m never going to write the bloody things, I figured it’d be better to throw them into the light of day and see what daylight makes of them. Here is a preliminary, first stab at a list of books I wish existed: books that haven’t been written yet, but could be.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I’m long on Visa</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/02/08/why-im-long-on-visa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I’m long on Visa" /><published>2020-02-08T21:49:05+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-08T21:49:05+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/02/08/why-im-long-on-visa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/02/08/why-im-long-on-visa.html">&lt;p&gt;Last month, Visa announced their intention to buy &lt;a href=&quot;http://plaid.com/&quot;&gt;Plaid&lt;/a&gt; for $5.3 billion dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaid provide an abstraction around bank accounts. They offer a developer-friendly API to query one or more of a user’s accounts. This allows startups and consumer products to offer financial analysis and services in a bank-agnostic way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the back of this purchase, and alongside my general growing interest in fintech, I’ve been becoming more and more bullish about Visa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why did Visa pay &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt; for Plaid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$5.3b is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of money. It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/jeffkauflin/2020/01/13/why-visa-is-buying-fintech-startup-plaid-for-53-billion&quot;&gt;somewhere between a 25x and 50x multiple of Plaid’s revenue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Plaid team are impressive, but at $5.3b, it’s got to be something strategic. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ricburton&quot;&gt;my friend Rich&lt;/a&gt; put it, when you’re counting in billions, it’s not an acquihire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if it’s not revenue, and it’s not (just) the team, what’s the strategic value in Visa’s owning Plaid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can think of three big reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. It solidifies Visa’s core business.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visa is a three-sided network. It provides the infrastructure to move money between consumers, merchants, and banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Visa works well, everyone benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers get instant access to credit, and can buy products from anywhere the card is supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merchants can accept payments from anyone, and no longer need to run back-office operations responsible for credit and payments, nor handle cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks can offer credit to consumers more easily, at higher interest rates, and collect fees from merchants to provide the aforementioned credit management services – and, in doing so, reduce merchants’ exposure to credit risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For arranging this service, Visa charge merchants and banks a percentage of each transaction. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/V?p=V&quot;&gt;underlying economics of the business&lt;/a&gt; are excellent: they have over a 50% profit margin, steady revenues, a long pedigree, and revenue still grows 10% year-on-year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaid can contribute to this core business, since an increase in fintech innovation is likely to increase transactions simpliciter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks can offer more, and better tailored, financial products to consumers. Visa can better integrate identity and security services with payments, reducing rates of fraud. More broadly, and more importantly, fintech &lt;a href=&quot;https://policyexchange.org.uk/publication/fintech-for-all/&quot;&gt;can, and will, bring finance to the under- and unbanked&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, Visa can leverage Plaid to shore up the existing network, make being a Visa customer more attractive, and create whole new demographics of customers in developing markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means more transactions, and more transactions means more transaction fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Plaid is a good business in its own right.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 25x to 30x multiple on revenue is large, but Plaid are still a relatively young company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaid offers Visa the opportunity to take fees from the “other side” of the consumer’s relationship with the bank: in GraphQL terms, the &lt;em&gt;queries&lt;/em&gt; against the bank account rather than the &lt;em&gt;mutations&lt;/em&gt; on it. This is somewhere Visa currently aren’t able to capture value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaid’s target customers are software engineers, but the institutions at the bottleneck to Plaid’s growth are banks. Now Plaid has the weight – and half-century of personal relationships – of Visa behind it, the product itself can grow substantially more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaid are also, so far, focussed heavily on the U.S. Fintech opportunities are global, so now Plaid can lean on Visa’s global reach to expand internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this said, Plaid could represent a significant income stream for Visa in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Plaid is part of a broader Cambrian explosion in fintech.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this purchase reflects a wider trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Stripe, Twilio, Algolia, and now Plaid have shown, making developers happy is big business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But making developers happy and productive also has serious downstream effects. It reduces the amount of time and money it takes to create new products. It encourages the development of new tools which themselves make developers happy and productive, effecting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techrepublic.com/article/the-open-source-decade-fueled-by-cloud-and-github/&quot;&gt;Cambrian explosion&lt;/a&gt; of new products and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the set of norms and tools developed around open source, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/dappradar-com/collateralization-and-composability-what-i-learned-at-defi-summit-london-2019-446005eee000&quot;&gt;composability&lt;/a&gt; in smart-contract technologies, making it easy, cheap, and secure for developers to access financial data will only accelerate the potential of technology –– and, crucially, along dimensions we can’t easily predict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: it increases the amount of innovation possible in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am at all correct about this, then Visa have shorn up their excellent business model, giving themselves access to an attractive new revenue stream, and now control a resource which has already, and will continue to be, central to sustaining and growing the fintech space, and, eventually, the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks&lt;/strong&gt; to Jessica Cooper, Richard Burton, Peter King, JS Denain, and Jonny Corrie for their notes and comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="fintech" /><category term="startups" /><summary type="html">Last month, Visa announced their intention to buy Plaid for $5.3 billion dollars.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Hour</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/02/01/book-hour.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Hour" /><published>2020-02-01T17:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T17:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/02/01/book-hour</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/02/01/book-hour.html">&lt;p&gt;A while ago, J and I noticed we’d lie in bed, fiddling with our phones for 30, 40, 45 minutes, an hour, many, most mornings, every morning. Sometimes our fiddling was productive, clearing emails, writing lists, researching some topic or other – but most of the time, it wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s easy to justify it to yourself if it’s AngelList, or LinkedIn: you’re keeping up with career options. Hacker News is obviously of great professional concern to a software engineer. Twitter keeps you wired into the zeitgeist. And, as for Facebook, what could be more important than friends and family?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point, of course, is that I’m fickle and distractible and the only thing that can salvage my mornings, whittle and form them out of the chaos, is to leave the matter out of my hands entirely. Leave motivation and bandwidth in the hands of a /system/, and make delivery an inevitability – or at least a reliable expectation – rather than something subject to whimsy and caprice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we built a system, and we call it “book hour”. Every morning, we read, at least, a few pages of a dead-trees paper book. Before touching our phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glimpse of analog before our days become digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can turn off your alarm. If somebody calls you, you’re allowed to answer. And it’s flexible: if you both agree on an exemption – early start, late start, got to catch a flight, etc. – then it’s allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it turns out that we rarely need an exemption, because beginning your day with a few pages of a book is actually a really nice thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, incentives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrot: you end up reading more, and, in a relaxed and controlled manner, gradually phase into your day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stick: If you touch your phone before reading a few pages, £10 goes in a savings pot in our joint bank account. When the pot reaches some amount, we take ourselves out for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good because it serves the psychological function of an incentive without any great real-terms material loss (we’d probably spend the money on eating out anyway.) It hurts without hurting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s effective, and I urge you to try it out if you too are looking for an easy and fun way to cut down on screen-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also, I think, illustrative of a more general approach to productivity, good work, and human happiness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build systems that minimise friction, and, where appropriate, align your incentives with your interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research is chaotic, but it’s okay, because we can build routines which encourage regular, structured work and limit the possibility of procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is chaotic, but it’s okay, because we can use spaced-repetition to minimise friction and &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;make long-term memory a choice&lt;/a&gt;. (As for incentives: how about an Anki hour?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shape and structure of data is chaotic, but it’s okay, because we can work with statically typed languages and write unit tests, both of which have all kinds of good upstream effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is chaotic, but it’s okay, because systems help tame it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">A while ago, J and I noticed we’d lie in bed, fiddling with our phones for 30, 40, 45 minutes, an hour, many, most mornings, every morning. Sometimes our fiddling was productive, clearing emails, writing lists, researching some topic or other – but most of the time, it wasn’t.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Government of No One: The Theory and Practice of Anarchism</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/01/09/kinna-government-of-noone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Government of No One: The Theory and Practice of Anarchism" /><published>2020-01-09T09:36:38+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-09T09:36:38+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/01/09/kinna-government-of-noone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2020/01/09/kinna-government-of-noone.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ruth Kinna, Pelican, 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most political ideologies have clear theoretical commitments. Liberalism: the individual as the primitive unit of society; his wellbeing subordinate to, or exhausted by, his freedom; doctrines of rights which circumscribe and define that freedom sitting at the base of any institutional arrangements. Socialism: the collective as the primitive; the individual’s wants subordinate to the group’s needs; a commitment to equality expressed in the common ownership of property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anarchism doesn’t really seem to fit. Anarchism, it seems to me, isn’t a political ideology at all: it’s more like a family resemblance, each anarchism approximating the others to a greater or lesser degree, but none admitting of a common core or shared basis. A fluid set of concepts aimed at achieving a form of radical egalitarianism rather than a concrete theory. Or perhaps, like conservatism, it’s more of a temperament, an inclination to gesture toward an outcome, rather than an explicit set of instructions to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Anti-capitalist egalitarianism’ holds the clue to unlocking it, says Kinna. But ‘anti-capitalist egalitarianism’ is hardly a clearer term than ‘anarchism’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one direction, it veers into a Kantian metaphysical liberalism of totally self-regulating agents. In another, it seems to collapse into communism. So the exponent of anarchism as &lt;em&gt;a distinctive tradition&lt;/em&gt; must not only explain anarchism on its own terms, but also situate it relative to the primitives of both the liberal and communist traditions, without relying on the primitives of either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that such a tradition can be cleaved out from between the two extremes. But it’s awfully difficult to do cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kinna does well to reveal anarchism’s parallel world of literature, art and debate. And she does a good job at casting the anarchist in a positive light, of repainting the out of the colours of a psychotic lover-of-chaos and into something a little more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not a good book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem is Kinna’s bias, and how it can hinder the book’s analytical power. This is advertised as a “sympathetic account”, and, to that extent, it delivers: she clearly has an affinity with the anarchist programme and is deeply immersed in its literature. But that’s also what makes it a tough book to follow: her familiarity means that she never really explains the basics, leaving the rest of us to reconstruct the edifice on which her explanations sit.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of an accessible introduction means that, to the outsider, it is a book of half-thoughts, non-sequiturs and passages groaning under the weight of technical terminology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rejection of domination unifies anarchists in shared struggles against the monopolization of resources and the centralization of power, representation, racism, imperialism and authority, while leaving the institutional and sociological mechanisms that explain it open to discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passages like the above are littered throughout the book, and yet the core concepts they turn on are never really explained. Is domination just shorthand for the ‘monopolization of resources and the centralization of power’? If not, what is it? And if so, why isn’t that compatible with federalism and some liberal anti-trust laws? Isn’t the &lt;em&gt;point&lt;/em&gt; of representation to centralise power? And what does it mean to centralise racism and imperalism? Why is authority a bad thing, its centralisation to be struggled against; doesn’t its goodness follow analytically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why couldn’t it be that these institutional and sociological mechanisms justify, not just explain the phenomena? Why accept these normative claims in the first place? Answers are not forthcoming, and so the whole thing feels incoherent, and in-groupy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is at its most incoherent and in-groupy in the section on education. Education is an important piece of the anarchist puzzle, since most people are in fact decidedly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; anarchists, and the political organisation it proposes requires individuals thinking and acting freely in anarchistic (i.e. egalitarian, ‘non-dominating’) ways. But anarchist thought on education, beyond just rehashing Marxist ideas about power sustaining power through ideology, are deeply unenlightening:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Knowledge is underpinned by linear, instrumental reasoning and this is manipulative and alienating … Education … comes, instead, through re-wilding: reconnecting to undomesticated, genuinely ecological and gentler systems of knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it goes on, and on, and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inaccessibility is this book’s original sin, but it also feels like it’s been rushed to print. Structurally, it’s organised thematically (Traditions, Cultures, Practices, Conditions, Prospects; followed by a set of anarchist biographies, which is mostly filler) and yet it focusses much on the historical development of the ideas, with the result that it keeps jolting, restarting; awkwardly lapsing into chronology, bumping against the ostensible thematic structure. Each insight and thinker tumbles into the next, presenting a cacophony of anarchisms, rather than a single unified theory. All of which means there’s little to no sustained argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest sin, however, is the lack of a genuine multi-sided discussion of political violence. Government actions are described as “horrifying brutality and evident injustice”; anarchist assassinations and violent direct action are described in much cooler, theoretical terms. Her sympathy means we miss any real discussion of these very important questions: the extent to which political violence is legitimate, necessary or just. And while I understand her reluctance to encourage the typical framing of anarchism as chaos, violence and disorder, violence is anarchism’s shibboleth, and any book on the subject ought to address it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a subtle, informed, nuanced debate of both why &lt;em&gt;these given thinkers&lt;/em&gt; find it legitimate, and under what conditions &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; might today, we get quiet acquiescence, defensiveness, deflection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One example of this is the debate about the ‘black bloc’ – the protest tactic associated with politic confrontation. Another is tactical diversity … resonant with the fluidity of historical anarchist activism, [which] encourages activists to ask whether a proposed action is ‘effective at generating power’ rather than ask whether it is ‘peaceful or violent’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s as close as we get to a discussion of this central issue, and it’s a much poorer book because of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of content in here. Kinna knows the tradition well. And it may be a valuable reference for somebody already au fait with the anarchist tradition; someone already predisposed to buy what it’s selling. But that’s not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some of the main concepts – domination, power, self-emancipation – echo Marx, but seem to be used in a different way; anarchism doesn’t share Marxism’s explanatory basis of historical materialism. Kinna never really explains what anarchists mean by these concepts, perhaps because they’re used so variously that there isn’t any common definition to give. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">Ruth Kinna, Pelican, 2019.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A few favourite LRB pieces</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2019/12/16/a-few-favourite-lrb-pieces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A few favourite LRB pieces" /><published>2019-12-16T20:20:29+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-16T20:20:29+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2019/12/16/a-few-favourite-lrb-pieces</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2019/12/16/a-few-favourite-lrb-pieces.html">&lt;p&gt;The London Review of Books has been a good companion to me, its prose crisp and clean and sometimes lyrical, its horizons broad. And while it’s often a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; political, too much on its sleeve – which hinders the analytical power of some of the more polemical pieces – I was a happy subscriber for years and recommend it to anybody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next month, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk&quot;&gt;the website’s paywall will be down&lt;/a&gt; and everything will be free. I figured I’d use this opportunity to link to a few pieces that I’ve read, enjoyed, not forgotten, or otherwise found interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v20/n23/christopher-hitchens/moderation-or-death&quot;&gt;Hitchens on Ignatieff on Berlin&lt;/a&gt;, Meany on &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n03/thomas-meaney/the-hagiography-factory&quot;&gt;Schlesinger Jr.&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v06/n10/bernard-williams/personal-identity&quot;&gt;Williams on Parfitt&lt;/a&gt;. Two pieces by the philosopher Amia Srinivasan, one &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v39/n17/amia-srinivasan/the-sucker-the-sucker&quot;&gt;on octopodes and consciousness&lt;/a&gt;, the other &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n06/amia-srinivasan/does-anyone-have-the-right-to-sex&quot;&gt;on politics and sexual desire&lt;/a&gt; are insightful and elegant. Jeremy Waldron, as ever, writes extraordinarily well &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v41/n17/jeremy-waldron/quibbling-wrangling&quot;&gt;on the shape and character of a politics given by a country’s constitution&lt;/a&gt;, and the tradeoffs (tradesoff?) involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Runciman is a regular contributor, and always interesting: &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v41/n19/david-runciman/his-fucking-referendum&quot;&gt;on David Cameron and the 2016 referendum&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v41/n12/david-runciman/steely-women-in-a-world-of-wobbly-men&quot;&gt;on Theresa May&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n19/david-runciman/i-didn-t-do-anything-wrong-in-the-first-place&quot;&gt;on Trump&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n15/david-runciman/the-impermanence-of-importance&quot;&gt;on Obama&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n01/david-runciman/what-was-it-that-drove-him&quot;&gt;on Gordon Brown&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n02/david-runciman/diary&quot;&gt;on artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt;. Jonathan Rée wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v37/n24/jonathan-ree/in-such-a-labyrinth&quot;&gt;on James Harris’s Hume&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v39/n06/jonathan-ree/horrible-heresies&quot;&gt;on Edwin Curley’s Spinoza&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve enjoyed articles &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v39/n09/adam-shatz/out-of-sight-out-of-mind&quot;&gt;on punishment and race in America&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v38/n15/stephen-sedley/resistance-to-torpor&quot;&gt;on Entick v. Carrington&lt;/a&gt;, and Geoffrey Hawthorn’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v37/n13/geoffrey-hawthorn/what-philosophers-dream-of&quot;&gt;reflections on my favourite philosopher, Bernard Williams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v40/n01/neve-gordon/the-new-anti-semitism&quot;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v39/n09/stephen-sedley/defining-anti-semitism&quot;&gt;interesting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v25/n16/judith-butler/no-it-s-not-anti-semitic&quot;&gt;pieces&lt;/a&gt; on antisemitism, zionism, Israel, its government, and the relations between all of the above; though none, in my opinion, quite understand the relevant problems, or render with enough subtlty the range of opinions amongst diasporic Jews –– and the dangers of getting the answers wrong. (Relatedly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_uk/article/ev8kxj/how-labour-could-start-to-solve-its-anti-semitism-crisis&quot;&gt;Ido Vock’s piece in Vice&lt;/a&gt; is the best article on this subject that I’ve ever read.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LRB occasionally jumps to and revives older texts, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v41/n01/michael-wood/don-t-worry-about-the-pronouns&quot;&gt;this review of my favourite Iris Murdoch novel, Under The Net&lt;/a&gt;. And sometimes &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v39/n16/patrick-cockburn/endtimes-in-mosul&quot;&gt;it doesn’t review texts at all, but instead tells contemporary people’s stories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the blogs, which always remain free, are also worth exploring. There’s a piece on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/blog/2019/january/academic-freedom&quot;&gt;Finnis, homosexuality, and academic freedom&lt;/a&gt; by Sophie Smith, which helped me see into a blind spot of my liberalism. Or there’s this piece on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/blog/2018/september/landmines-in-the-sahara&quot;&gt;Landmines in the Sahara&lt;/a&gt; by an old acquaintance of mine, Matthew Porges; his piece on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/blog/2017/july/killing-a-camel&quot;&gt;Killing a Camel&lt;/a&gt; is also good. Srinivasan also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/blog/2017/january/remembering-derek-parfit&quot;&gt;a short obituary on Parfitt, which is charming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lrb" /><category term="books" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">The London Review of Books has been a good companion to me, its prose crisp and clean and sometimes lyrical, its horizons broad. And while it’s often a little too political, too much on its sleeve – which hinders the analytical power of some of the more polemical pieces – I was a happy subscriber for years and recommend it to anybody.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some thoughts on the election</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2019/12/14/some-thoughts-on-the-election.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some thoughts on the election" /><published>2019-12-14T09:33:15+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-14T09:33:15+00:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2019/12/14/some-thoughts-on-the-election</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2019/12/14/some-thoughts-on-the-election.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are a few thoughts, mostly unstructured, and in no particular order, on the general election:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why is everybody so surprised that so many working-class Northern seats went Tory? The moment Labour prevaricated over their Brexit position was the moment they lost these seats. Delivering Brexit matters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is an empirical point I’ve not tested, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2017/05/15/voting-intention-regional-breakdown-apr-24-may-5&quot;&gt;it looks like&lt;/a&gt; May did the bulk of the work in 2017. Johnson’s – and Cummings’ – brilliance was to leverage it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would only work if they managed to convince the right voters in the right places that Parliament – &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; Parliament – was the block, and needed replacing. While the rest of us were moaning about prorogation, and mocking Johnson for losing all those votes, he was quietly winning the election – and he hadn’t even called it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Momentum brigade are just as bad after the election as they were before it. I saw more on my feed from Corbynites trashing the Liberal Democrats than I saw from them criticising the Conservatives. Or even making a positive argument for Labour.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Relatedly, ‘the media has a right-wing bias’ and ‘FPTP disadvantages us’ are terrible excuses for losing an election. Tough. Of course the media have a right-wing bias. Of course FPTP is a preposterous system that offers the Conservatives an entrenched advantage. We’ve known this for years. The Left needs to learn to work within these constraints rather than decry them. And, this election, Labour &lt;em&gt;singularly&lt;/em&gt; failed to do so. This is on you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(By the way, Labour, you had a chance to get rid of FPTP.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll leave my thoughts on antisemitism in the Labour Party for another day. But they got everything they deserved, and their loss is something to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Liberal Democrats have been bruised, but they’ve been bruised before. And it wasn’t all bad. Increased majorities, a gain in vote share, moving into second place. As my friend E said, if they had held East Dunbartonshire but lost Jamie Stone, they would be saying it was a good night.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think it’s likely that ‘presidentialising’ the campaign – “Jo Swinson’s Liberal Democrats” – killed it more than the revoke Article 50 overreach. As people got to know her more, people liked her less.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously, the Conservatives ran a remarkably ugly campaign too, and their victory should be lamented. This was not a victory of ideas. It was the final nail in the coffin that Thatcher and Blair built. Democracy’s epistemic function is over.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That being said, I’m a little more optimistic about a Johnson government with a seventy-odd-seat majority rather than a minority, or a 5-seat majority, particularly one enabled by working-class Northern seats. These voters are still, quite rightly, naturally suspicious of the Conservatives. He has very little good will indeed. I think he understands this – his “you’ve lent me your vote” comment is telling.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turkeys voting for Christmas? It’s this arrogance and superiority, this smug self-indulgent paternalism (which I’ve indulged in myself) that lost the election for people like me and the ideas I believe in. Of course the average voter doesn’t have the time, skills, knowledge, whatever to make comprehensive, informed decisions. Their vote still counts, and their voice should still be heard. It’s up to politicians to craft a narrative – which is to say, an &lt;em&gt;abstraction&lt;/em&gt; of ideas and policy proposals – that resonates with people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, it’s easy to forget that most people are instinctively conservative. A lot of people don’t like immigration, or are (reasonably) fearful of its effects. A lot of people don’t like taxes. An increasing number of people have a strongly negative aesthetic response to perceived political correctness, and the social justice movement more broadly. We can debate any of these individual positions until we’re blue in the face, but for a lot of people it’s just a gut thing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It now seems clear to me that Remain is no longer an option, democratically or otherwise. We’re not getting a People’s Vote. We are going to leave the European Union, at least formally speaking, in January. In this sense, the debate is over.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In another sense, it’s just beginning. Remainers who care about preserving the tangible benefits of EU membership need to plan, regroup, and lean on interest groups, business, the trades unions, local government and the other relevant institutions of civil society to protect or otherwise emulate those benefits in a Brexit context. Democracy doesn’t end between elections (even though it might feel like it does sometimes.) Nor is it only implemented in Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot of people in my circles – &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/acgrayling&quot;&gt;including people who have taught me&lt;/a&gt; – are arguing that there’s no mandate for Brexit since the Tories were elected without a majority of the popular vote, or polling suggests slight support for remain, or whatever. This misses the point. We have procedures, whatever issues from those procedures are called democratic, and Brexit, loosely defined, has now issued from those procedures twice. If you don’t like it, change the procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One might reply with illegal contributions, Russian hacking, lies on busses etc. It’s horrendous, I agree. But I’m starting to think that the fact that enough people &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; they voted for Brexit for their own valid reasons, and voted subsequently for the Tories to &lt;em&gt;reaffirm&lt;/em&gt; that Brexit position, is enough to make the implementing the outcome both legitimate and indeed required, at least morally speaking (though perhaps not epistemically). You can’t tell people they’re empowered and then not let them wield that power –– certainly not twice. The social contract is a fragile thing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m aware of the slippery slope in the point above. I still haven’t figured out what all this means for my theoretical commitments. As with everything in the social sciences – and possibly value theory – it’s a moving target.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was nothing unpatriotic about campaigning for a People’s Vote in the GE. The courts’ suspension of Johnson was not traitorous. People like Dominic Grieve will be looked upon kindly by history. The Remain movement was important, urgent, and its cause noble.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But we’re having a different conversation now. And I think Remainers need to realise this, lest we beat on, boats against the current. There’s nothing noble in that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These opinions are, of course, liable to change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">Here are a few thoughts, mostly unstructured, and in no particular order, on the general election:</summary></entry></feed>