<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-09T20:19:00+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jamie on Software</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">AlphaTensor, Taste, and the Scalability of AIs</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/10/09/alphatensor-scaling.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AlphaTensor, Taste, and the Scalability of AIs" /><published>2022-10-09T10:26:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-09T10:26:00+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/10/09/alphatensor-scaling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/10/09/alphatensor-scaling.html">&lt;p&gt;This week’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deepmind.com/blog/discovering-novel-algorithms-with-alphatensor&quot;&gt;AlphaTensor&lt;/a&gt; announcement shows not only that AI is getting really good at doing things, but also that DeepMind are really good at getting AI to do things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their approach is a variant of the deep reinforcement-learning-guided Monte Carlo tree search that they have applied so successfully to playing Chess and Go. What they have done, very effectively, is to design a game with the objective of finding the most efficient tensor multiplication algorithm for a matrix of some dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of important object-level takeaways from the paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The search space for various algorithms and mathematical techniques is enormous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Existing algorithms and techniques are often not provably the most globally efficient; there is room to improve&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We can improve an algorithm by paying attention to its implementation, as well as its theoretical virtues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also teaches us some things about the meta-level, and the benefits of DeepMind’s distinctive approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DeepMind’s approach is scaleable vertically: the more time and compute they spend on a task, the more they can achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DeepMind’s approach is scaleable horizontally: the more tasks they apply their approach to, the more tasks they can achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these points suggest something important about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/Scaling-hypothesis#scaling-hypothesis&quot;&gt;scaling hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weak version of the scaling hypothesis claims that most of what we need to improve AI performance is more compute. All we need to do is scale up the computational and data resources of a sufficiently scalable model, and we’ll get much better performance. Give the right model architecture enough data, and enough compute/time, and our problem is solvable (up to the phyical limits, or something like that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I begin my argument, I’ll make a presupposition: we won’t get to AGI. My hunch is that AGI is a bit of a chimera, and that progress in AI will consist mostly in the discovery and application of specialist models for narrow-domain problem solving. Some models may generalise to some extent, some may not. But over time the progress of narrow-domain AIs will far outstrip the progress in broad-domain AIs, and the market will reallocate resources accordingly.[^1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this presupposition, we can ask an important question: does the weak scaling hypothesis hold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world in which AI is applied to solving narrow-domain issues, AI researchers have two major tasks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How should they decide which tasks to work on?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How should they encode a given problem such that it is tractable for AI to solve?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) is hard to decide &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt;, because it will depend on the path-dependence progress of science (and the supporting AI). Utility-maximising functions might be helpful here: what task has the lowest cost and the highest utility? But a lot will be baked into ‘cost’ and ‘utility’, and the various cost bases of tasks will change depending on how the technology evolves, what data is available, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, AI researchers will develop heuristics, industry and academic partnerships, new data sources, etc., and that will help narrow down the range of tasks susceptible to quick resolution. In short, AI researchers will rely on &lt;em&gt;taste&lt;/em&gt; and experience to guide their decisions over the medium- and long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) is more analysable from first principles. Tasks need to be encoded in such a way as to make them solvable by the model: the model architecture needs to be designed in such a way as to not preclude the task; the input needs to be readable by the model; the set of training data needs to be large and varied enough to prevent overfit, and contain sufficient signal to allow generalisation to inputs outside that dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most importantly, the game needs to be designed &lt;em&gt;such that it’s the sort of game that the model can play&lt;/em&gt;. This is what DeepMind seem especially good at: they are able to express, e.g., protein folding, or tensor decomposition, in the form of a game that their RL agent can play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ability – being able to reorganise a question in the form of a model-appropriate game – doesn’t look nearly as susceptible to Moore’s Law-style exponential speed-ups. Researchers’ insights and abilities – in other terms, researcher productivity – don’t scale exponentially. It takes time and energy and the serendipitousness of a well-functioning research lab to cultivate them. Scaling compute down to an effective cost of zero doesn’t help if we’re not using these models to attack the right issues (1) in the right way (2). The marginal next unit of compute will exhibit diminishing returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if that’s the case, then it’s clear that &lt;em&gt;compute isn’t the bottleneck&lt;/em&gt;. The bottleneck, instead, will be humans figuring out which problems to tackle (1) and how to regiment them, encode them, and design games/reward systems to get AI to solve them (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeepMind have the absolute best people on the planet working on this stuff, and it takes them time and huge amounts of resources. So we end up back at &lt;em&gt;taste&lt;/em&gt;. Researchers need time and experience to develop taste, and the ability to apply heuristics and deep domain knowledge – something much more ineffable and difficult to scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t of course mean that there won’t be wonderful progress in many, many domains, brought about by ‘merely’ scaling the compute available. Even Kuhn is at pains to stress that ‘normal science’ is progress! But it does mean that the scaling hypothesis doesn’t necessarily scale research output at the same rate, at least not without AGI –– and without this, my best guess is that progress will be bottlenecked long before.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai" /><summary type="html">This week’s AlphaTensor announcement shows not only that AI is getting really good at doing things, but also that DeepMind are really good at getting AI to do things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links, September 2022</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/10/01/links-september-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links, September 2022" /><published>2022-10-01T14:22:45+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-01T14:22:45+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/10/01/links-september-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/10/01/links-september-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;Wrapped up my work with Fei Labs this week, and am now unemployed again, poking around the edges of opportunities and building a stronger sense of what I want to work on next. My book on product engineering with Ethereum is coming along well; I should have the first draft done in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been rewatching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/title/80025678&quot;&gt;The Crown&lt;/a&gt;, partly in preparation for the new season, partly to revisit the life of Elizabeth II, and most of all because I have had several casual conversations with friends on various topics in 20th-century British political history, and I wanted a lightweight set of touch points, nudges toward various prime ministers and political events that I might read into more deeply. As a result, almost all of my reading time has been taken up with television. It’s amazing how easily that can happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did, however, manage to reread &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Stubborn-Attachments-Prosperous-Responsible-Individuals/dp/1732265135&quot;&gt;Stubborn Attachments&lt;/a&gt; by Tyler Cowen. It was much less surprising and enjoyable on rereading, but I suppose that’s a sign of a book whose ideas seem to be more mainstream, whose arguments are more familiar and plausible, whose memes have sunk in to my brain. If I have any criticisms now, it’s that it isn’t ambitious or controversial enough; he caveats the demand for growth by demanding sustainable growth; he builds a broader normative pluralism into a notion of ‘Wealth+’; both of which feel more like a concession to the zeitgeist rather than a serious commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somebody fed the lyrics of ‘Imagine’ into an AI and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sundellviz/status/1574492250620542980&quot;&gt;asked it to write new verses.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jnixy/status/1559568512485470209&quot;&gt;America over-incacerates and under-polices.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&quot;https://nautil.us/lose-weight-the-slow-and-incredibly-difficult-way-239703/&quot;&gt;preposterous and charming post&lt;/a&gt; from Randall Munroe: how much of the Earth’s mass would you have to relocate to space in order to lose 20lbs of weight?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminder that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9lqW3pQDcUuugXLIpzcUdA&quot;&gt;YouTube has some 400 episodes of Buckley’s Firing Line interviews&lt;/a&gt;, and they’re still extremely good. (Has anybody put the audio into a podcast stream yet?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dkedrosky/status/1566611402030063622&quot;&gt;The top five papers assigned in economics classes since 1990.&lt;/a&gt; Might look into producing a similar list for philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Sarris’s series on building a home &lt;a href=&quot;https://simonsarris.substack.com/p/designing-a-new-old-home-defining&quot;&gt;continues to be a delight&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/interview-vitalik-buterin-creator&quot;&gt;Noah Smith interviews Vitalik&lt;/a&gt;, mostly on proof-of-stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hunter_owens/status/1575884725935185925&quot;&gt;Some boring statistics.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="links" /><category term="books" /><category term="politics" /><category term="statistics" /><category term="economics" /><category term="housing" /><summary type="html">Wrapped up my work with Fei Labs this week, and am now unemployed again, poking around the edges of opportunities and building a stronger sense of what I want to work on next. My book on product engineering with Ethereum is coming along well; I should have the first draft done in the next few weeks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links, August 2022</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/09/01/links-august-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links, August 2022" /><published>2022-09-01T14:43:12+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T14:43:12+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/09/01/links-august-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/09/01/links-august-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;Richard Rhodes’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Making-Atomic-Bomb-Richard-Rhodes/dp/1471111237/&quot;&gt;The Making of the Atomic Bomb&lt;/a&gt; was the highlight this month, a detailed and incredibly scientifically literate story of the agglomeration effects of genius and the construction of the atomic age. A long and detailed book but interesting ideas and stories on every page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continually impressed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.stripe.com&quot;&gt;Stripe Press&lt;/a&gt; and thoroughly enjoyed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Where-Flying-Car-Storrs-Hall/dp/1953953182&quot;&gt;Where Is My Flying Car?&lt;/a&gt; by J. Storrs Hall. We need more techno-optimistic books. Hope and ambition are technologies too, and should be developed and promoted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also finished &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Anarchy-Rise-Fall-India-Company/dp/1408864371&quot;&gt;The Anarchy&lt;/a&gt; by William Dalrymple. Had the chance to chat to Dalrymple last month and his enthusiasm and perspicuity for this subject is astounding. The EIC was a violent and predictable and transformative institution, but it was at the same time path-dependent and its success subject to utterly unpredictable chance. Every time I read history I’m taken aback by the fragility of the world we’ve inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a short post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/27/state-adjacent-institutions.html&quot;&gt;state-adjacent institutions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US &lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/science/2022/07/us-regulators-will-certify-first-small-nuclear-reactor-design&quot;&gt;approved a small nuclear reactor design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noah Smith on &lt;a href=&quot;https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/industrial-policy-starts-with-semiconductors&quot;&gt;CHIPS and chips&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/four-reasons-why-gdp-is-a-useful&quot;&gt;four reasons why GDP is a useful number&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceplusplus.org/visions/index.html&quot;&gt;Vision papers in science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regress Studies on &lt;a href=&quot;https://regressstudies.substack.com/p/is-it-okay-to-finish-books&quot;&gt;how to choose books&lt;/a&gt; and why you should allow yourself to be dragged into books you suspect you won’t finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An older thread from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/_ArnaudS_/status/1427003439540756485&quot;&gt;Arnaud on books on the history of modern computing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gleech.org/aaronson&quot;&gt;The best of Scott Aaronson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://conference.nber.org/conf_papers/f166369.pdf&quot;&gt;Knowledge spillovers in Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our IV approach estimates substantial returns to face-to-face meetings with overidentification tests suggesting we are capturing the returns to serendipity that play a central role in the urban theories of Jane Jacobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scanbot.io/blog/types-of-barcodes/&quot;&gt;Types of barcodes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good Visa threads on a cluster of related ideas: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1436393464468369408&quot;&gt;do what you want to do&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1199907654602125312&quot;&gt;do it a lot&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1455243916773494784&quot;&gt;tell others to do what they want to do&lt;/a&gt;. I had a great chat with Visa at Future Forum, and his temper and mode and writing is lovely in a happy-go-lucky, auto-optimistic kind of way. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.visakanv.com/blog/&quot;&gt;His blog&lt;/a&gt; is also excellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuño Sempere on &lt;a href=&quot;https://nunosempere.com/blog/2022/08/20/fermi-introduction/&quot;&gt;decomposing quantitative problems into simpler questions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="links" /><category term="books" /><category term="politics" /><category term="science" /><category term="startups" /><category term="urbanism" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">Richard Rhodes’s The Making of the Atomic Bomb was the highlight this month, a detailed and incredibly scientifically literate story of the agglomeration effects of genius and the construction of the atomic age. A long and detailed book but interesting ideas and stories on every page.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">State-Adjacent Institutions</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/27/state-adjacent-institutions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State-Adjacent Institutions" /><published>2022-08-27T14:59:28+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-27T14:59:28+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/27/state-adjacent-institutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/27/state-adjacent-institutions.html">&lt;p&gt;From Dominic Cummings’s recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://dominiccummings.substack.com/p/snippets-5-no10-farce-ukr-tory-strategy&quot;&gt;‘Snippets 5’&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NSN searched for people who wanted to start new schools that we intended to allow under new legislation then worked with them on their application.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It developed specific ideas for how the system should work. Unlike normal think tanks, it worked at the extreme detail end of the spectrum, like drafting actual forms that the DfE could use.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We thought that if we helped people develop specific projects and could actually bend the bureaucracy, we could get ‘Free Schools’ going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is interesting, because it suggests a model for &lt;em&gt;state-adjacent&lt;/em&gt; institutions that support the functions of the state without being tied to the bureaucracy or subject to the incentives. Something somewhere in the midpoint between a management consultancy, a think tank, and a training institute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like this sort of model is beneficial in specific circumstances:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where there is considerable state funding for a certain industry / project / goal&lt;/strong&gt;, where ‘considerable’ is relative to the industry / project / goal. (You need more money to make a new nuclear power plant design than you do a school.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where access to that funding is reasonably competitive.&lt;/strong&gt; This means it needs to be accessible to SMEs or small teams, rather than just Serco, G4S, the major universities, and the other big boys.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where the government department distributing the funding is receptive to introductions, advice, support&lt;/strong&gt;. A lot of the benefits seem to come from new ideas being introduced revisited through a feedback loop, so the department must be flexible enough to integrate the state-adjacent institution into its decision making – or, at least, leave its door open to such input. Generally, I suspect, departments are only really flexible in this sort of way during their first few years and for a year or two after a major shake-up (eg DoE under Gove).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few ideas where this could be useful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An ‘ARIA Attractor’: finding individuals / teams with audacious projects, helping them refine their proposals, and using the knowledge gained from the search to help shape the department’s broader research focus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An analogous attractor for the UKRI / NIH / other ‘normal science’ funding bodies, with an emphasis on speeding up the funding application process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standards setting and guidance for navigating the planning system, but beyond a simple planning consultancy. A team of people who work hard to befriend and effectively lobby local planning teams, giving developers large and small the opportunity to boot up to the activation energy required to get anything built. It would be useful to focus on local authorities with a recent change in governance, or with an especially acute housing problem, where the demand to do something is greater.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A company to abstract away the medical licensing and compliance process and help guide new teams / University spin-offs to apply for medical licenses. Medical software, in particular, is notoriously hard to get adequate licensing for. A team dedicated to building solutions and increasing governmental awareness of these issues, working with funding bodies and NHS clinical commissioning groups, could meaningfully move the needle on what innovation we permit in the medical space (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scarletcomply.com&quot;&gt;Scarlet&lt;/a&gt; are doing interesting things adjacent to this idea.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating and supporting these sorts of state-adjacent institutions could be an important &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/pfbLKnJmDKYSPPCEW/four-focus-areas-of-effective-altruism&quot;&gt;focus area&lt;/a&gt; for a movement like Effective Altruism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it could also be a powerful new framing for start-ups themselves: many of these ideas could grow into profitable businesses as well as institutions with positive-sum state/business interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking the question “how can the private or non-profit sector smooth over the relationship between the state and others?” is a subtly different question – and one with (in many cases perhaps) more leverage than the simpler question “how can the state do things more effectively?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because it refocuses the conversation on what can be done &lt;em&gt;practically&lt;/em&gt;, today, without needing large-scale systemic reform, without needing to push through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dominiccummings.com/tag/procurement/&quot;&gt;ossified systems of government purchasing&lt;/a&gt; and permits that sit in deeply suboptimal equilibria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="housing" /><category term="startups" /><summary type="html">From Dominic Cummings’s recent ‘Snippets 5’:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links, July 2022</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/03/links-july-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links, July 2022" /><published>2022-08-03T11:35:28+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-03T11:35:28+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/03/links-july-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/08/03/links-july-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;ETHCC Paris, The Idler Festival, dinners at the Liberal Club, work on the book, actual work, and learning to fly; it’s been a busy month in which I deadlifted 100kg for the first time, only read a couple of books, submitted the first few chapters of &lt;strong&gt;Products, Protocols, and Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;, and have found myself exhausted. I am more energised when I am productive, and more productive when I am energised, so ascertaining how to bootstrap myself into either productivity or energy is I think a high-leverage activity with which I’ll be experimenting for the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most important thing I read this month was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Eichmann-Jerusalem-Report-Banality-Evil/dp/024155229X/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;sr=&quot;&gt;Eichmann in Jerusalem&lt;/a&gt;. I didn’t quite realise how much of a journalist Arendt was, and look forward to reading more of her political theory in the future. It’s rare, nowadays, to go from in-the-trenches journalism to academic theorising. (Counterexamples: Gramsci, sort of? Maybe Robert Caro? Anne Applebaum, perhaps?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also supplemented Arendt with Richard Evans’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Third-Reich-Power-1933-Hearts/dp/0141009764&quot;&gt;Third Reich in Power&lt;/a&gt;, the second volume in the series. I read the first volume maybe a decade ago and enjoyed it. The second was more of a slog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just finished &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Hard-Drive-Making-Microsoft-Empire/dp/0887306292/ref=sr_1_1?crid=D7B2ZBP7Q351&amp;amp;keywords=hard+drive+bill+gates&amp;amp;qid=1659523562&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sprefix=hard+drive+bi%2Cstripbooks%2C798&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Hard Drive&lt;/a&gt;, a book about Bill Gates and the early days of Microsoft. Gates was a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more competitive and ruthless than I thought – and I thought he was pretty competitive and ruthless!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/All-Out-War-Britains-Political/dp/0008215154&quot;&gt;All Out War&lt;/a&gt; by Tim Shipman. Fantastic political journalism, no agenda, just the steady beat and the sporadic bursts of a battle unfolding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryancbriggs/status/1544321988101128195?utm_source=substack&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&quot;&gt;Political science is horribly underpowered.&lt;/a&gt; I am in a cynical mood right now, so don’t expect these findings to change much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/johncoogan/status/1546921877586604032&quot;&gt;A logarithmic map of the entire universe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good post from Tanner &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholars-stage.org/the-fall-of-history-as-a-major-and-as-a-part-of-the-humanities/&quot;&gt;on the decline of history majors&lt;/a&gt; and the relationship between the sciences and the humanities. Also a very well-written letter &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/criq.12675&quot;&gt;on decolonising the curriculum&lt;/a&gt; and the contradictions inherent in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something very distinctive about the ‘long-form interviews with macho men for a predominantly working-to-lower-middle-class white male audience that leans right’ format, and I can’t quite put my finger on what it is. It’s far from anti-intellectualism: the hosts and their guests are smart and eager to grapple with complicated ideas. It’s not quite one-sidedness, because they can surprised you. It’s almost an aesthetic property, a flavour of self-assuredness, the eschewing of the effete. Whatever it is, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nwK_XLFOm_I&quot;&gt;this interview with Erik Prince&lt;/a&gt; was swimming in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wonderful lecture &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n068fel-W9I&quot;&gt;on the F-22 Raptor and the engineering decisions behind it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://justinehsmith.substack.com/p/two-years-on-substack&quot;&gt;Justin E. H. Smith reviews his two years on Substack.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brie Wolfson wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://every.to/p/what-i-miss-about-working-at-stripe&quot;&gt;on the work culture early-days Stripe&lt;/a&gt;. A reminder that hard work is a feature, not a bug – and the symptom of a thriving culture, not the cause of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordinary citizens have &lt;a href=&quot;https://infoproc.blogspot.com/2016/01/american-and-chinese-oligarchies.html&quot;&gt;essentially no influence over government in the United States&lt;/a&gt;. What the elites want, they generally get. It’s amazing that US society is generally so stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/how-we-will-fight-climate-change?utm_source=substack&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&quot;&gt;End degrowtherism now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pricedout.org.uk/resources/podcast/&quot;&gt;good old episodes on the PricedOut podcast&lt;/a&gt;, covering planning reform, the commercial incentives of house building, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="links" /><category term="books" /><category term="politics" /><category term="science" /><category term="housing" /><category term="books" /><summary type="html">ETHCC Paris, The Idler Festival, dinners at the Liberal Club, work on the book, actual work, and learning to fly; it’s been a busy month in which I deadlifted 100kg for the first time, only read a couple of books, submitted the first few chapters of Products, Protocols, and Platforms, and have found myself exhausted. I am more energised when I am productive, and more productive when I am energised, so ascertaining how to bootstrap myself into either productivity or energy is I think a high-leverage activity with which I’ll be experimenting for the rest of the year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links, June 2022</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/07/02/links-june-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links, June 2022" /><published>2022-07-02T20:30:59+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-02T20:30:59+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/07/02/links-june-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/07/02/links-june-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;Found myself in somewhat of a funk this month, low on energy and motivation. My usual menu of neuroses bubbling up and my usual response; fits-and-starts of bouyancy followed by lethargy. Unhappy with my work. I think I need a holiday. And twenty more IQ points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, not much writing, just &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/27/wallets-as-identity.html&quot;&gt;Wallets As Identity&lt;/a&gt;, a rough first draft of a chapter from the Ethereum book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began five books but only finished one: Feyerabend’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Against-Method-Paul-K-Feyerabend/dp/1844674428&quot;&gt;Against Method&lt;/a&gt;. I intend to write in more detail about it, because it was both very good and also rather illegible. After some effort, I think I have a clear idea of what he is trying to do, but I can’t see how his arguments don’t collapse into a much broader scepticism. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JamieRumbelow/status/1535955057966989313&quot;&gt;Here’s a Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; with some quotes I enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unabridged edition of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audible.co.uk/pd/A-History-of-Britain-Volume-1-Audiobook/B0094OI6U4&quot;&gt;Simon Schama’s History of Great Britain series&lt;/a&gt; is wonderful – Schama writes so well – and it’s currently included with any Audible subscription, although that will change this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sriramk.com/memos.html&quot;&gt;A collection of memos&lt;/a&gt; ‘written for an internal audience’, mostly business and technology but some politics too. Diaries and letters and other documentary on how the sausage gets made gives you a good sense for 1. the trade-offs involved in absolutely everything, something that is easy to consider intellectually and much harder to feel intuitively, 2. how chaotic and unregimentable progress is a priori, and 3. the sheer variability of approaches and styles of success and failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Nielsen writes on &lt;a href=&quot;https://michaelnotebook.com/eanotes/&quot;&gt;effective altruism&lt;/a&gt; and his take on its problems providing a moral core for an individual’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend pointed me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/1FPKMooGfbOGzESM1G2ffC?si=e2cb4c6bb8d6440b&amp;amp;nd=1&quot;&gt;this Dylan B-side&lt;/a&gt;, from the Blood on the Tracks sessions. Lovely and sad and detached. Dylan’s narrator is always at arm’s length from his subject, even when he’s singing about himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two useful reviews of The Future of Fusion Energy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://martin.kleppmann.com/2022/01/03/future-of-fusion-energy.html&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; from Martin Kleppman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/your-book-review-the-future-of-fusion&quot;&gt;the other&lt;/a&gt; from the Astral Codex Ten book review contest: the former reviews the book, the latter reviews its content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby Ord on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/2104/2104.01191.pdf&quot;&gt;the knowability of the Edges of the Universe&lt;/a&gt;; and a fun lecture from Stuart Armstrong on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zQTfuI-9jIo&quot;&gt;how we might get there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a bit of context on the jurisprudential questions that underly the Roe v Wade debates, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jmv5Tz7w5pk&quot;&gt;a chat between Scalia and Breyer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here’s a beautiful photograph of a new(-ish; May 2020) impact crater found on Mars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://static.uahirise.org/hipod/ESP_065745_0980.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Impact crater on Mars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="links" /><category term="books" /><category term="ethereum" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="music" /><category term="space" /><category term="science" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">Found myself in somewhat of a funk this month, low on energy and motivation. My usual menu of neuroses bubbling up and my usual response; fits-and-starts of bouyancy followed by lethargy. Unhappy with my work. I think I need a holiday. And twenty more IQ points.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wallets As Identity</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/27/wallets-as-identity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wallets As Identity" /><published>2022-06-27T10:14:21+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-27T10:14:21+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/27/wallets-as-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/27/wallets-as-identity.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a very rough first draft of a chapter from my upcoming book on Product Engineering in Ethereum. Any and all feedback welcome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technologists use metaphors to make &lt;strong&gt;skeuomorphic links&lt;/strong&gt;, bridging old paradigms to new. The ‘desktop’ and ‘trash can’ and even the keyboard is a form of skeuomorphic link, giving users of a new platform enough conceptual and aesthetic resources to make sense of it, to feel familiar, connected to it. Computers and interfaces are physical, and rely on all the same instinctual responses, the same clusters of predispositions and responses attached to entities in the physical world. So new technologies can co-opt these instincts by creating these skeuomorphic links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most common example of skueomorphich linkage in crypto is the metaphor of the ‘wallet’. This post argues that it is one of the most misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick diversion on the structure of metaphors: metaphors behave by implying certain things about the subject based on the object. Good metaphors are good when the subject does indeed resemble the object in those ways. Good metaphors also have the nice property of illuminating the subject of the metaphor in ways that the reader doesn’t expect. A good metaphor can help reveal the shapes and contours of the subject by making us consider the subject from a new angle. ‘All the world’s a stage’, Jacques soliliquises in &lt;strong&gt;As You Like It&lt;/strong&gt;, and the entrances and exits and performance that this equivalence conjures up help illuminate the human condition, revealing it to be a form of entrapment, confinement to a pre-determined script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What, then, does the metaphor of ‘wallet’ imply? It suggests a few features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A wallet holds things&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A wallet holds a specific sort of thing, namely financial things (such as credit cards and cash)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A wallet is a physical item, and plays the various roles that physical items do, such as signalling style, wealth, and status&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crypto wallets – what we’ll call ‘accounts’ from now on to avoid confusion – have none of these features. Accounts don’t hold things: accounts represent identity. Accounts aren’t limited to interacting with financial products: they interact with anything representable on the blockchain. Accounts, of course, aren’t physical items: they are an abstraction over an individual on a ledger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth stopping at this point and asking why any of this matters. Isn’t it just a shallow, semantic dispute? No. Because as well as being illuminating about the subject, a metaphor can often &lt;strong&gt;constrain&lt;/strong&gt; our understanding of the subject, especially if it becomes the primary mechanism through which the subject is known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has happened with the wallet metaphor in crypto, which is why I believe it’s especially important to pay attention to what wallets actually are, how the metaphor shapes our thinking, and how it limits our thinking too. All the world is a stage, maybe, but if it is we still have plenty of freedom to improvise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accounts-dont-hold-things&quot;&gt;Accounts don’t hold things&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An account is a pair of public and private keys. A private key is used to generate a public key, and the public key is used to generate an address. So when you see account addresses such as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;0xd8dA6BF26964aF9D7eEd9e03E53415D37aA96045&lt;/code&gt; (one of Vitalik’s accounts), what you’re really seeing is the result of passing Vitalik’s private key through the set of cryptographic functions that produce these addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of how this works are interesting, but out of the scope of this post. All we need to know for now is that this process is &lt;strong&gt;deterministic&lt;/strong&gt;, in the sense that it returns the same value for the same input, no matter how often you run it, and &lt;strong&gt;irreversible&lt;/strong&gt;, in the sense that it’s very very hard to get the private key from the wallet address.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you know the private key then you can generate the public key, but you can’t (easily) go in the other direction. This is one of the reasons why it’s so important to keep your private key private: your private key is the one piece of information somebody needs to get access to your account. Fortunately, most users don’t have to worry about the content of the private key at all: they can use wallet software that holds the private key in a secure way. For product engineers, you’ll always need to keep in mind that the private key is sacred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this link to the wallet metaphor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I lied a little: accounts do ‘hold’ something. They hold ether, the native token of the Ethereum blockchain. But this is by communal assent: a group of people, incentivised to follow the same set of rules, collectively agree that a certain amount of ether is owned by a specific account, and another amount of ether is owned by a different account. It’s the collective assent that underwrites the ownership claim, not the account itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve got cash in your wallet, you actually do have cash in your wallet. A portion of the ‘state’ of the money-system is in your pocket. If you’ve got ether in your account, you’ve got a claim on the group for the amount of that ether. It’s a guarantee, secured by cryptography and incentives, that when you decide you want to do something with that ether we’ll all agree that you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m also telling the truth: accounts don’t really hold that much at all, and the notion of ‘holding’ your ether and your tokens is a euphemism. Your account is the mechanism of a record of ownership. The state is not in your pocket, it’s ‘over there’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem a little opaque, so let’s consider some code. One of the clearest examples of how accounts don’t actually hold anything is the ERC-20 token standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This standard is the core primitive in DeFi, the basic lego brick upon which we build this cathedral. It offers a consistent interface for smart contracts that behave as a record of ledger. Contracts have to choose to implement it – that’s why it’s a standard, not a rule – but those that do share the same methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can distil the essence of ERC-20 down to only two function signatures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;function balanceOf(address _owner) public view returns (uint256 balance);
function transferFrom(address _from, address _to, uint256 _value) public returns (bool success);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The actual standard contains more than these two methods, but the rest are for convenience, expedience, and extensions to the functionality, rather than being central to the model of how tokens are represented by contracts that implement it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two functions tell us everything we need to know about a piece of state. What is that piece of state? It’s a mapping from address to the number of tokens owned by that address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mapping(address =&amp;gt; uint256) public balanceOf;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;balanceOf&lt;/code&gt; is a map – otherwise known as a dictionary, or an associative array – from an owner to the total amount owned. The total amount owned of what? The token that the contract represents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to find out how much of the token we own, we call &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;balanceOf&lt;/code&gt;, passing our address. If we want to send our tokens to somebody else, we call &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;transferFrom&lt;/code&gt;, passing our address, the recipient’s address, and the amount we wish to send. The token contract does the work in updating the list it holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about this carefully: &lt;strong&gt;a token is just a list of who owns the token&lt;/strong&gt;, plus a bit of metadata (such as the token’s name and symbol).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your account doesn’t ‘hold’ anything. It doesn’t know anything about the token, per se. It just gives you a way of identifying yourself as the owner of some amount of the token. And a token is just a piece of code that understands how to update this &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;balanceOf&lt;/code&gt; map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple and powerful idea, because the token contract is able to stipulate its own rules and policies around who can transfer, who can be transferred, and what the balance is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could stipulate that only a specific whitelist of addresses should be able to receive the token, for instance, restricting ownership of the token to a known set of individuals. You could exclude certain addresses. You could require a certain amount of ether in exchange for the token, or even a certain amount of another token in exchange for the token. You could even &lt;strong&gt;change the amount transferred when somebody transfers it&lt;/strong&gt;, deducting a fee. In other words, you can implement a monetary policy, controlling how the token enters the market, how it leaves it, and how it flows around between participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accounts-arent-limited&quot;&gt;Accounts aren’t limited&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the token contract is the mechanism for recording who owns what, and stipulating the rules that govern that ownership, your account isn’t limited to holding financial instruments like cash or credit cards. Tokens can be used to represent basically anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some tokens represent non-fungible assets, things that can’t be exchanged for another asset just like it. You will have heard of NFTs, and NFTs are token contracts much like the ERC-20 contract we just discussed. The biggest difference between ERC-20 and ERC-721 – the basic standard for representing NFTs – is that the parameters of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;transferFrom&lt;/code&gt; function are slightly different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;function transferFrom(address from, address to, uint256 id) public virtual;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ERC-721 contract introduces the notion of an &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;, and requires that the pair &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(owner, id)&lt;/code&gt; is globally unique. So a specific token – that described by the contract and the specific ID the contract defines – is owned by one and only one person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFTs are often used for digital art or collectibles, but they can be used to represent ownership of lots more. In time, they may be used to represent ownership of real-world assets: houses, cars, paintings, bottles of wine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFTs can also be used for interesting, crypto-native use cases: Uniswap v3, for instance, mints an NFT that represents a deposit to a specific pool within a specific price range. Each deposit has its own custom configuration, and so the pool mints an NFT that represents your specific deposit with your specific settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fungible tokens, too, can be used to represent many more types of things than just those that map to financial value. They can represent governance rights, as they do with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TRIBE&lt;/code&gt; token, which grants the right to vote on proposals of the Tribe DAO. (At the time of writing, most governance tokens grant voting rights on a quantity basis: if you have more tokens, your vote represents more of the. But this isn’t the only model for governance design made possible by the ERC-20 token standard). They can also represent other sorts of values, such as carbon credits, or reputation, or points accumulated in a game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that the ‘wallet’ metaphor suggests a constraint on the sorts of things that can be ‘held’. Since accounts don’t ‘hold’ things, the design space for what sorts of ownership and participation claims they can represent is much, much bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accounts-arent-physical-items&quot;&gt;Accounts aren’t physical items&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem like a silly point to make, but the fact that accounts aren’t physical items runs a little deeper than the obvious. Accounts aren’t physical items: they are abstractions over an individual, a face you can show to the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this means that your accounts aren’t tied to one place. If you know your private key, you can use your account in whatever interface you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that &lt;strong&gt;different interfaces can display different aspects of the same account&lt;/strong&gt;. Some interfaces – CHECK: such as what? – put an emphasis on NFT collectibles, a kind of gallery. Others might focus on the purely financial aspects of the account, its deposits and loans and investments. Perhaps an interface could be built around governance, showing the proposals and votes and engagements with protocols. Perhaps another could be built around whatever gaming tokens the account has claims to. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start to consider these sorts of product implications of the fact that accounts aren’t physical items, it makes you realise that the design space for account interfaces is co-extensive – overlapping with – the design space for tokens themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also pushes the sorts of signalling properties we mentioned earlier elsewhere. Perhaps people do signal with their &lt;strong&gt;wallet software&lt;/strong&gt; – i.e. their account interfaces – a little, using a newer or more feature-complete piece of software to indicate the sort of user they are, the sorts of things they are interested in. But the account itself is a very lightweight thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because it’s lightweight, it can be transported, as we’ve discussed. It can also be ‘hosted’ on-chain, which opens up the possibility of smart contract wallets and multi-signature wallets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accounts-are-identity&quot;&gt;Accounts are identity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is an account, then, if not a wallet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My answer: an account is an &lt;strong&gt;identity&lt;/strong&gt;. It is a way of informing other participants that you are who you say you are. It is a username and password. It is a mechanism to authenticate yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If accounts are identity, then it means you can separate out your identities depending on different contexts of usage. You might use an account to trade, another account to represent your investments, a third to hold your claims to any artwork or collectibles. You might use accounts for different platforms with different risk profiles, or with different privacy considerations. You can separate out your identities in whatever way you choose, isolating your public, on-chain behaviour into different categories. The ownership of a private key gives you full control over what aspect of yourself you wish to show to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products built on Ethereum need to understand this multiplicity of identities, and implement support for it in a deep way. We’ll see how this works more concretely in other posts. But for now, consider that &lt;strong&gt;your identity goes with you wherever you take it&lt;/strong&gt;. And where your identity goes, so do your claims of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, combined with the standardisation of interfaces such as ERC-20 and ERC-721, increases the power of the interfaces we can build substantially. To take a simple example: a tool for listing whatever ERC-20-compatible tokens are ‘held’ by an account will work with &lt;strong&gt;any token that meets the requirements of that interface&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s as if PayPal could support all currencies from day one, with no extra development work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wallet metaphor is generally broken, then, and can severely constrain your imagination vis-a-vis what accounts are capable of. For sure, there are ways in which an account can seem like a wallet: when you lose your account, just like your wallet, you lose the money in it; to that extent, the metaphor is true. But it’s true for different reasons. If you lose a physical wallet you’ve actually lost the cash inside it. If you lose a crypto wallet, you’ve lost your ability to prove you are the person who owns the cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are likely to continue using the term ‘wallet’, since that’s what the community uses, and there’s not much marginal benefit in changing this sort of heavily-entrenched meme. I use ‘wallet’ and ‘account’ interchangeably. But I hope this chapter has given you a sense of how accounts actually work, and why the design space for them is an awful lot bigger than a piece of folded leather that you keep in your pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How hard? There’s no better way than guessing at random. Ethereum private keys are 256 bits. Since a bit has two possible states, guessing a 256 bit sequence correctly at random has a chance of 1/2^256. There are ~10^78 atoms in the observable universe, which is roughly 2^260. Account addresses are only 160 bits long, which means that there are multiple possible private keys, but 2^160 is still a very big number, equivalent to a little bit less than the total number of atoms on Earth. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ethereum" /><summary type="html">This is a very rough first draft of a chapter from my upcoming book on Product Engineering in Ethereum. Any and all feedback welcome!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links, May 2022</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/02/links-may-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links, May 2022" /><published>2022-06-02T15:26:48+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-02T15:26:48+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/02/links-may-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/06/02/links-may-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;May was a fine month with lots of social engagements, less writing than I wanted, but quite a lot of reading. I ran the Edinburgh Marathon, my first marathon ever, in four hours and 33 minutes. I wrote a piece on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/24/decentralisation-is-a-tradeoff-space.html&quot;&gt;Decentralisation as a trade-off space&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare for a debate with my friend David, I read two books on the history of housing development: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/All-That-Solid-Housing-Disaster/dp/1846147158&quot;&gt;All That is Solid&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Municipal-Dreams-Rise-Council-Housing/dp/178478740X&quot;&gt;Municipal Dreams&lt;/a&gt;. The latter was very good. The former descended into Tory-bashing in the key of Owen Jones, which might be righteous but is also a little tiresome. I also read bits of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Order-without-Design-Markets-Cities/dp/0262038765&quot;&gt;Order Without Design&lt;/a&gt;, which was truly excellent; it’s good to see urban theory that grounds itself in, and has respect for, economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Diaries-Two-People-Alastair-Campbell/dp/0099493462&quot;&gt;the second volume of Alastair Campbell’s diaries&lt;/a&gt;, covering 1997-1999 and the first few salvos of a triumphantly New Labour. The diary format is excellent, since you get an obviously singular perspective as it unfolds. I hadn’t realised quite how little communication mattered in the civil service prior to Blair; lots of Campbell’s agonies involved getting various govt departments to coordinate messaging, routing comms through Number 10. I also had very little idea of how much work went into the Good Friday agreement, or how tenuous it was. Many many chances for it to fall apart. Had Paisley or Trimble or Adams woken up on the wrong side of bed on the wrong morning and the whole thing would have been doomed. From inside government policy seems much more chaotic and stochastic than I had suspected (which might be a reason to be less worried, at least on the margin, about &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/07/30/meditations-on-moloch/&quot;&gt;Moloch tendencies&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Shadow-Moon-Challenging-Tranquility-1965-1969/dp/B01DJS9E1A&quot;&gt;In the Shadow of the Moon&lt;/a&gt; while falling asleep most nights, a very thorough set of biographies and history of the Gemini missions, up to Apollo 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for other links, and continuing on the theme of housing, I also read a few good papers worth reading if the subject appeals to you. Anthony Breach’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.centreforcities.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/2019-06-13-Capital-cities-how-the-planning-system-creates-housing-shortages-and-drives-wealth-inequality.pdf&quot;&gt;Capital Cities: How the Planning System Creates Housing Shortages and Drives Wealth Inequality&lt;/a&gt; was extremely clear and thorough, UK-specific, and perfect for preparing for an argument with David. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worksinprogress.co/issue/the-housing-theory-of-everything/&quot;&gt;The Housing Theory of Everything&lt;/a&gt; helps drive home why this matters so much. YIMBY is a moral argument as much as an economic one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Campbell’s diaries got me on a bit of a New Labour kick, so I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/p09wgbfk/blair-brown-the-new-labour-revolution-series-1-episode-1&quot;&gt;last year’s excellent series&lt;/a&gt; on Blair and Brown and the 13 years of New Labour government. I’ve also been enjoying &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.acast.com/s/the-rest-is-politics&quot;&gt;The Rest is Politics&lt;/a&gt; podcast, hosted by Campbell and Rory Stewart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarkesh Patel wrote a good post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dwarkeshpatel.com/p/barbell-strategies&quot;&gt;applying the ‘Barbell Strategy’ to everyday life&lt;/a&gt;: reframing habit formation and intellectual projects in terms of oscillating between intense focus on one thing and the simplest, lowest-effort thing possible –– which is often nothing at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Shiriff is writing some truly excellent, deep work on the technical substrate of the Apollo missions. This is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.righto.com/2022/05/talking-with-moon-inside-apollos.html&quot;&gt;a post on the premodulation processor&lt;/a&gt;, the signal combinator and splitter in the command module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now make clocks &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nist.gov/news-events/news/2022/02/jila-atomic-clocks-measure-einsteins-general-relativity-millimeter-scale&quot;&gt;so sensitive that they can detect the relativistic difference caused by being one milimetre deeper in the Earth’s gravity well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook open-sourced &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/facebookresearch/metaseq/blob/main/projects/OPT/chronicles/OPT175B_Logbook.pdf&quot;&gt;a logbook documented while building and deploying&lt;/a&gt; one of their NLP models. More companies and people should do this sort of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I signed a contract with Apress this week to publish a book on Product Engineering on Ethereum. My aim is to raise the relative status of product engineers – those of us who build everything around smart contracts, UIs, tooling, infrastructure – and explore how the unique processing model of Ethereum puts important constraints on the way we build software. I’ll be posting some pieces here as I work through the first draft, so keep an eye out if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="links" /><category term="ethereum" /><category term="housing" /><category term="urbanism" /><category term="economics" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="politics" /><category term="science" /><category term="books" /><summary type="html">May was a fine month with lots of social engagements, less writing than I wanted, but quite a lot of reading. I ran the Edinburgh Marathon, my first marathon ever, in four hours and 33 minutes. I wrote a piece on Decentralisation as a trade-off space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decentralisation is a trade-off space</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/24/decentralisation-is-a-tradeoff-space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decentralisation is a trade-off space" /><published>2022-05-24T21:36:22+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-24T21:36:22+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/24/decentralisation-is-a-tradeoff-space</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/24/decentralisation-is-a-tradeoff-space.html">&lt;p&gt;When you ask a crypto-sceptic what decentralisation means wrt crypto, they offer these sorts of properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many nodes are run across many jurisdictions; computation happens in a way that can’t ever be shut down or censored&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Individuals can access the system for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SGBarbour/status/1528432799941808130&quot;&gt;whatever nefarious purposes&lt;/a&gt; they wish, without the need for inter alia KYC checks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power is completely diffused rather than concentrated in any one party; therefore, no individual party is responsible, either legally, operationally, morally, or all of the above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sorts of conditions actually refer to what I’ll call ‘maximal decentralisation’ – a system which is decentralised in every way possible, up to whatever point of diminishing marginal returns seems appropriate. It is different from decentralisation, which refers to a system that can have more or less participation, more or less accessibility, more or less diffused power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem like an unimportant semantic distinction, but not all semantic distinctions are meaningless, and some are indeed important. How we define our terms matters, because it limns the shape of what we build and gives us criteria against which we evaluate our success. Moreover, if we disagree over what we mean by a term like ‘decentralisation’, we end up arguing fruitlessly. We exchange claims and both sides miss the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of crypto people also believe, somewhat reflexively, that we should be aiming for maximal decentralisation. The worst crypto-fanatics are just as ideological as the worst crypto-sceptics. This is a problem. People shouldn’t be fanatical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost every category, maximalism is bad. It ties you into a priori commitments, which reduce your optionality and cripple your ability to adjust to new facts. Strong beliefs are important, but they should generally be held weakly. It also makes you much more likely to act tribally. Humans are tribal, and ‘decentralise everything’ can become a rallying cry, a standard around which troops array for battle. It makes technical questions political, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/9weLK2AJ9JEt2Tt8f/politics-is-the-mind-killer&quot;&gt;politics is the mind-killer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crypto people shouldn’t be fanatical, because computing is the art of the science of trade-offs, and ‘decentralisation’ gives us a lot more room for manoeuvre than either its critics or fanatics seem to allow. Trade-offs are useful, and understanding the trade-off space is most of the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that crypto people don’t actually want decentralisation per se, because when you ask why decentralisation matters, you get answers like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It makes the technology more accessible and more censor-resistant. It gives broader access to a broader set of people, especially those less well-served by existing financial infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means that their motivations are prior to decentralisation. They want accessibility! They want censorship-resistance, and greater equality of opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want other things. Decentralisation means more competition, and more competition means more innovation. (Diversity is good! Let a thousand flowers bloom!) The ideas being generated and built upon by the crypto community are not commodities: they are meaningfully new contributions to a meaningfully new technology stack; we get more ideas when we have a more competitive space, and we get more competition when people are able to use the technology and gain access to the liquidity needed to prove the new ideas out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More subtly, another important corollary of decentralisation is that it leads to implicit coordination through standards. And standards make composability possible. So decentralisation is also good because it leads to more composable technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how then can we think about decentralisation in a more yielding way? How can we make it more supportive of our broader aims – accessibility, censorship-resistance, competition, composability – without holding ourselves hostage to its demands, on the one hand, or giving our opponents a stick to beat us with, on the other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we must realise that decentralisation is a spectrum. It isn’t a binary state. Systems can be more or less decentralised, and what we’re actually arguing over is how decentralised a given system should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we must realise that there are different sorts of components in a web3 system, and decentralisation doesn’t just apply to the computation. There are the RPC nodes, the API interface into the computation layer: they can be more or less decentralised. There are frontends, which serve user-friendly interfaces to interact with the contracts via these RPC nodes: they can be more or less decentralised. There is the data itself, the state, which can be more or less decentralised. There is the liquidity, the value locked in the system, which can also be thought of as more or less decentralised. Etc etc etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we must realise that how decentralised a given system should be depends on the purpose of that system. A platform that needs to perform a lot of complicated computation can trade off a bit of decentralisation by pulling some computation off-chain.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Many web3 frontends use the semi-decentralised &lt;a href=&quot;https://thegraph.com/en/&quot;&gt;The Graph&lt;/a&gt; to provide indexing, trading off some centralisation in exchange for faster data retrieval. Almost no web3 frontend uses decentralised alternatives to the substrate of internet technologies on which they sit, DNS and web hosts and friends. This is all okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, we must realise that often just the ability to decentralise means that the goals of decentralisation can be achieved. In other words, centralised parts of a decentralised system don’t immediately make the system totally centralised – it’s not a binary – and therefore useless vis-a-vis the goals of decentralising. This is one of the reasons why &lt;a href=&quot;http://moxie.org/2022/01/07/web3-first-impressions.html&quot;&gt;moxie&lt;/a&gt; is wrong: while it’s true that there are a few dominant hosts of RPC nodes, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alchemy.com&quot;&gt;Alchemy&lt;/a&gt;, it is very easy to run nodes, and would not be especially capital intensive to start competitors.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Alchemy won’t abuse their power, because if they did it would be extremely easy to compete with them. The fact that the computation layer and its implementation – e.g. the geth codebase – is permissionlessly accessible means that there are downstream pressures on people who use those implementations to not abuse their power. ‘Counterfactually decentralised’ is a real thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most importantly, we must realise that we have a choice, as builders and consumers, and that the truest expression of a decentralised system is one in which individuals are given freedom to engage (in the broadest possible sense) with the project (in the broadest possible sense) –– on their own terms. On this count, at least, crypto seems to be doing well, even though aspects of it are indeed centralised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is that crypto-fanatics and -sceptics alike seem to think that the fight is over whether decentralisation is ‘necessary’, which is about as helpful as asking whether a bridge is strong enough, or a cow is fat enough, or a child is confident enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Necessary for what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I hope to write more about the relationship between fact-questions and values-questions in the future. I feel intuitively and reflexively annoyed by the post-modern adage that everything is political, because grounding facts-questions in values removes our one objective standard, our one ability to offer a response beyond ‘I don’t like it’, not to mention all the other socio-psychological effects that make respectful debate impossible and seem to have poisoned the epistemic commons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ethereum does this itself by not permitting contracts to autonomously call other contracts; mechanisms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://makerdao.world/en/learn/vaults/liquidation/&quot;&gt;MakerDAO’s liquidation process&lt;/a&gt; need to be triggered by off-chain actors incentivised through rewards. There are ways of solving the obvious trust problems, usually through incentives, if you believe they are problems. Much of the time they are not. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We know this, since there actually are &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/en/developers/docs/nodes-and-clients/nodes-as-a-service/&quot;&gt;a bunch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.cloudflare.com/web3/ethereum-gateway/&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://infura.io&quot;&gt;competitors&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ethereum" /><category term="decentralisation" /><summary type="html">When you ask a crypto-sceptic what decentralisation means wrt crypto, they offer these sorts of properties:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links, April 2022</title><link href="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/01/links-april-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links, April 2022" /><published>2022-05-01T09:10:04+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-01T09:10:04+01:00</updated><id>https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/01/links-april-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/05/01/links-april-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;April has been busy and changeable – mirroring the weather, I suppose – I began a new role at &lt;a href=&quot;https://fei.money&quot;&gt;Fei Labs&lt;/a&gt; and am getting settled. I wrote three pieces on this blog: something technical on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/04/02/hd-wallets-and-network-switching.html&quot;&gt;HD wallets and network switching&lt;/a&gt;, something equally technical &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/04/03/a-quick-note-on-web_accessible_resources-in-Safari-Web-Extensions.html&quot;&gt;about Safari iOS extensions&lt;/a&gt;, and the aforementioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamieonsoftware.com/2022/04/06/solidity-fridays-transmissions11.html&quot;&gt;notes on the t11s episode of Solidity Fridays&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding my own contributions, this was a good month for interesting reading. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Star-Builders-Nuclear-Fusion-Planet/dp/1474611583&quot;&gt;The Star Builders&lt;/a&gt; is a very accessible and fast read on the why and how of nuclear fusion. It’s a contribution to the – I think underrated – genre of “here’s a plausible pathway to some major scientific discovery, and a set of good reasons to be optimistic we’re on that pathway” science writing. One for the techno-optimists’ bookshelves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily St. John Mandel’s new novel, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Sea-Tranquility-Emily-John-Mandel/dp/1529083494&quot;&gt;Sea of Tranquility&lt;/a&gt;, is out, and is splendid. I found some of the science fiction elements a little bit hamfisted, and this is definitely Mandel finding her voice and her groove. But it’s worth reading, especially if you’ve read Station Eleven (one of the best novels I’ve read in the last few years) and The Glass Hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Seven-Brief-Lessons-Physics-Rovelli/dp/0141981725/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1651344159&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Seven Brief Lessons on Physics&lt;/a&gt; was enjoyable, too. Best supplemented by something more technical, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I just finished &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/London-Under-Peter-Ackroyd/dp/0099287374&quot;&gt;London Under&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Ackroyd. I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; Ackroyd’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Life-Thomas-More-Peter-Ackroyd/dp/0749386401&quot;&gt;biography of Sir Thomas More&lt;/a&gt;, but hadn’t read any of his other books. He’s an excellent writer. There were a handful of places where I thought he made non-sequiturs – the sort of non-sequiturs quite common in a certain style of proto-academic culture writing – but I’m being really picky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The excellent Noah Smith did &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oaMgZSd3gV4&quot;&gt;an interview&lt;/a&gt; with the excellent David Roberts on climate change, climate tech, climate activism, writing in public. Both combative and thoughtful throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/tracers-in-the-dark-welcome-to-video-crypto-anonymity-myth/&quot;&gt;challenging post on child abuse videos&lt;/a&gt; and a global coordinated effort to bust a specific site and its clients. A long and difficult read but very worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something to keep an eye on – an economics lab &lt;a href=&quot;https://start.edgeryders.eu/page/15452&quot;&gt;imaginging systems through science-fiction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’ve woken in a sweat, panicked that you’re not subscribed to enough substacks (subsstack?), &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30983517&quot;&gt;here’s a list&lt;/a&gt; of good, subject-specific newsletters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very very good and comprehensive and thorough &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdrprimer.org/read&quot;&gt;guide to direct carbon renewal&lt;/a&gt;. We need to do more here; Stripe and others have &lt;a href=&quot;https://frontierclimate.com&quot;&gt;launched an advanced market commitment to help&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stripe &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/blog/expanding-global-payouts-with-crypto&quot;&gt;have also launched crypto payments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the conversation, not the end of it, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://austinvernon.site/blog/starshipsuperweapon.html&quot;&gt;some reflections on SpaceX’s technologies and warfare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really enjoyed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worksinprogress.co/issue/londons-lost-ringways/&quot;&gt;this article on the urban history and development of London’s planned and, blisfully, abandoned Ringways&lt;/a&gt;, the persistence of political structures and the perversity of political incentives, and the pitfalls of top-down urban planning. Works in Progress is putting out a lot of excellent stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of my normal reading, I listened to three audiobooks this month, all spacey or science-related content. Another for the techno-optimist bookshelf, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Case-Space-Revolution-Spaceflight-Possibility/dp/B08CVTT36C&quot;&gt;The Case for Space by Zubrin&lt;/a&gt; was good fun, opinionated, rigorous and rather inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Forces-of-Nature/dp/B01NA0F2DD&quot;&gt;Forces of Nature&lt;/a&gt;, from the same authorship of The Planets (mentioned last month), was also splendid. The narrator is truly excellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/080322639X&quot;&gt;Into That Silent Sea: Trailblazers of the Space Era, 1961-1965 by French and Burgess&lt;/a&gt; is part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B088T4M553&quot;&gt;a broader series&lt;/a&gt; of histories on various topics in spaceflight. The whole series is pretty good, with only a few exceptions, and this isn’t one of them. Meticulous and narrative-driven, I learnt a lot about Gagarin, Leonov, the Mercury Seven, and the politics that made it all happen. I’ll be continuing this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also &lt;a href=&quot;https://calendly.com/jamierumbelow&quot;&gt;finally got a Calendly set up&lt;/a&gt;, so if you’d like to chat, feel free to book in a call.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="links" /><category term="science" /><category term="london" /><category term="books" /><category term="climate" /><summary type="html">April has been busy and changeable – mirroring the weather, I suppose – I began a new role at Fei Labs and am getting settled. I wrote three pieces on this blog: something technical on HD wallets and network switching, something equally technical about Safari iOS extensions, and the aforementioned notes on the t11s episode of Solidity Fridays.</summary></entry></feed>